One of my missions in life is to make getting proficient on the mainframe as simple and painless as possible.
我人生的使命之一，就是讓學習大型主機變得簡單且輕鬆。
However, there is such a thing as oversimplifying, and I get a little set off when I hear someone explain datasets as,
不過，過度簡化是有問題的，當我聽到有人這樣解釋資料集時，我會有點反感，
well, a dataset is just a file.
「資料集不過是一個檔案。」
And it's a dangerous generalization to make because for a few basic examples, yeah, it appears like a dataset is the same thing as a file,
這是一個危險的概括，因為以幾個基本例子來看，資料集看起來的確像檔案，
and they have a lot of the same characteristics.
它們有許多相同的特性。
But once you dig just a little bit deeper, you'll see there are some very important differences to know about.
但稍微深入一點，你會發現有一些重要的差異必須知道。
So first off, a dataset can be either sequential or partitioned.
首先，資料集可以是順序的或分割式的。
A sequential dataset is full of entries called records, and they go one right after the other, after the other, after the other, like a stack of pancakes.
順序資料集由稱為紀錄的條目組成，這些紀錄一個接一個排列，就像一疊鬆餅。
A partitioned dataset has a directory and members.
分割式資料集有目錄和成員。
The directory keeps track of all the members, so they don't have to be in order, and it also makes it possible for each member to be accessed directly.
目錄會追蹤所有成員，因此成員不必依順序排列，也能直接存取每個成員。
This is what kind of closely resembles the files in a folder structure you're probably familiar with.
這很像你熟悉的資料夾結構中的檔案。
So what do we use these datasets for?
那我們用這些資料集做什麼？
Use datasets for storing data.
資料集用來儲存資料。
If you're dealing with data that comes out of a program, it typically comes out line by line, and each line is recorded as a record.
程式輸出的資料通常是一行一行，每行作為一筆記錄。
In a sequential dataset, you've just got record after record, output after output.
在序列資料集中，記錄一筆接一筆，輸出接著輸出。
And it could be a series of passenger numbers or a listing of company names.
可能是一系列乘客號碼或公司名稱清單。
In a partitioned dataset, that same data gets stored as records within the PDS members.
在分割式資料集中，相同資料以記錄存在於PDS成員中。
And if you're writing or reading a text file, each line in that is a record.
讀寫文字檔時，每行是一次記錄。
So in a sequential dataset, records go into a dataset, and in a partitioned dataset, records go into members, which go into a dataset.
序列資料集的記錄進入資料集，分割資料集的記錄進入成員，再進入資料集。
There are two kinds of partitioned datasets, PDSs and PDSEs.
分割式資料集有兩種：PDS和PDSE。
PDSEs are an enhancement to the original PDS design, and have greater flexibility in sizing, faster searching, and automatically reclaim space when members are deleted.
PDSE 是對原始 PDS 設計的增強，具有更靈活的容量大小、更快的搜尋速度， 且成員刪除時可自動回收空間。
There's only a few places in ZOS where you're required to use a PDS instead of a PDSE.
在 z/OS 中只有少數地方必須使用 PDS，不能用 PDSE。
Everywhere else, people just use a PDSE.
其他地方大多數人都使用 PDSE。
There's also a very powerful type of dataset called a VSAM dataset.
還有一種非常強大的資料集稱為 VSAM 資料集。
That stands for Virtual Storage Access Method.
它代表 Virtual Storage Access Method。
And that's another acronym I had to look up just to tell you what it stands for, because everyone just calls it VSAM.
這也是我特地查過才知道的縮寫，因為大家通常都直接稱它為 VSAM。
So just call it VSAM.
所以就直接叫它 VSAM。
A VSAM dataset uses a series of keys to reference the actual pieces of data being stored.
VSAM 資料集使用一系列鍵值來參考實際存放的資料片段。
It actually quite closely resembles something like a NoSQL database, and it's used primarily by applications directly, since you can't display or edit its contents in something like ISPF.
它相當類似 NoSQL 資料庫，且主要供應用程式直接使用，無法用 ISPF 類工具顯示或編輯內容。
There's a lot to VSAM, and it has many uses, but because we'll be using ISPF for many of our labs, we'll be focusing on PDS datasets.
VSAM 功能很多、用途廣泛，但因為我們實驗多用 ISPF，主要會專注於 PDS 資料集。
A PDS dataset name can be anywhere from one to a series of 22 joined name segments.
PDS資料集名稱可由1至22個連結的名稱區段組成。
So, Jeff.Loves.Pizza is a valid dataset name.
因此，Jeff.Loves.Pizza是有效的資料集名稱。
It's also true.
這也是正確的。
Jeff is the high-level qualifier, Loves is another qualifier, and Pizza is the low-level qualifier.
Jeff是高層限定詞，Loves是另一個限定詞，Pizza是低層限定詞。
Obviously, qualifiers are separated by a period, and you can use a maximum of 44 characters in total, including the periods.
限定詞以句點分隔，總長最多44個字元（含句點）。
So, you've got these qualifiers separated by periods.
你有這些用句點分隔的限定詞。
Each qualifier must begin with an alphanumeric character, or the special character, at, hash, or dollar sign.
每個限定詞必須以字母數字或特殊字元@、#、$開頭。
The characters after that can be alphanumeric, special, or numeric, and each qualifier must be one to eight characters in length.
之後的字元可為字母數字或特殊字元，每個限定詞長度為1到8個字元。
Dollar sign 32.4.Pizza is a valid dataset name, as long as the 4 is spelled out F-O-R and not the number 4, because a dataset qualifier can't start with a number.
Dollar sign 32.4.Pizza是有效名稱，只要4是拼成F-O-R， 而非數字4，因為限定詞不能以數字開頭。
$32 for pizza? That's a little ridiculous, right?
$32 for pizza？這有點荒謬，對吧？
Anyway, sys1.ParmLive, well, that better be a valid dataset name.
不管怎樣，sys1.ParmLive 必須是有效的資料集名稱。
So, i.sure.do.love.this.awesome.system is a valid dataset name, because it has less than 44 characters total.
i.sure.do.love.this.awesome.system 是有效的資料集名稱，因為總長度不到44個字元。
You should try to have some order, though, and not use names that might confuse people.
不過你應該保持命名有條理，不要用會讓人困惑的名稱。
Just because you can do it, sometimes doesn't mean you should.
能做不代表有必要做。
Now, to use a dataset, it must first be allocated, and allocated just means it exists in a way that we can reference it as an object.
要使用資料集，必須先配置，配置代表它存在且我們能以物件參考它。
We have a link to it.
我們有指向它的連結。
So, before we can type anything into a dataset, we need to allocate it, since the dataset we're typing into is going to take up space.
輸入內容到資料集前須先配置，因為資料集需要佔用空間。
Makes sense, right?
這樣說合理嗎？
One of the easiest ways of allocating a dataset is through the ISPF panel, made specifically for datasets.
配置資料集最簡單的方法之一是透過專為資料集設計的 ISPF 面板。
So, in ISPF, if we go to option 3 for utilities, and then option 2 for dataset, we can use option A for allocate.
在 ISPF 裡，選擇選單3（Utility），然後選2（Data Set），再用 A 選項配置。
And we can take ISPF's suggestions for naming a dataset using these three fields, the project, group, and type.
我們可以利用 ISPF 建議的專案、群組與類型這三個欄位來命名資料集。
That's a good start.
這是一個不錯的開始。
Or I can just type out the name of the dataset that I want down here.
或是我也可以直接在下面輸入想要的資料集名稱。
It's up to you, but if you want to have more than three qualifiers, you'll have to use the field down here, labeled other partition sequential or VSAM datasets.
這取決於你，但若想有超過三個限定符，必須使用下方標記為其他分割序列或 VSAM 資料集的欄位。
On the next screen, you need to decide if you want a sequential or a partition dataset.
下一個畫面，您需要決定想要建立的是序列式資料集還是分割式資料集。
The steps are largely the same, except that for a sequential, you specify zero blocks for the directory, because a sequential dataset has no directory.
步驟大致相同，不過對於序列式資料集，目錄區塊數必須設為零，因為它沒有目錄。
Everything is just in order.
一切都是按順序排列。
To create a PDSE, you specify the word library in the dataset name type field over here.
若想建立 PDSE，需要在資料集名稱類型欄位指定 library 一詞。
If you did this right, you'll get this message up top saying dataset allocated.
若操作正確，畫面上方會顯示成功配置資料集的訊息。
And if you get anything else, just go back and retrace your steps. It's probably something simple.
如果出現其他訊息，請回去重複步驟，通常是簡單的錯誤。
Either way, now you see why datasets are not the same thing as files.
不管怎樣，現在你應該了解資料集和檔案並不相同。